Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850, 1888-2000s and undated, bulk 1920-2008 RL.00936
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives
1850, 1888-2000s and undated, bulk 1920-2008
1920-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company
RL.00936
230 Linear Feet
The North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives document the founding and development of N.C. Mutual in Durham, N.C., and contribute to the historic record on African American businesses and entrepreneurship in the South and in the United States. Dating from 1850 to 2008, with the majority of the items created from 1920 to 2008, the material covers nearly every aspect of N.C. Mutual's operations, management, and milestones. There are corporate office files, including the offices of five company presidents; annual statements; reports; surveys; memos; legal and financial papers; original life insurance policies; training material; programming and outreach files; many ephemera and artifacts; and thousands of historical photographs of staff and their families, offices, buildings, and Durham scenes. Significant businessmen represented in the papers include founders John Merrick and Aaron Moore; and presidents Bert Collins, Joseph Goodloe, William Kennedy Jr., William Kennedy, III, Charles C. Spaulding, Asa T. Spaulding, and current president James H. Speed. The collection is especially rich in print material, including many issues of three company publications: The Mutual (1903-1929), The Whetstone (1924-1998), and The Weekly Review (1925-1998). It is also notable for its assemblage of material on United States African American history, including much information on other companies, and public relations material dating from the earliest years to present times, including advertising ephemera, advertising campaigns, and other related items. Other materials document NCM's outreach to the African American community throughout its history to counter racism, unemployment, and diseases by means of public health programs, church affiliations, mentoring, and scholarship programs. Over one hundred selected digitized photographs and a few documents are also available online. Acquired and curated jointly by the North Carolina Central University's University Archives, Records and History Center and the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture at Duke University.
Access Restrictions
Collection is partially restricted.
Files in the Office of the President Subseries are restricted for 25 years from the last year of each presidency. Permission to access these records must be granted by NC Mutual in writing prior to use.
Personnel files have been separated from the Office of the President Subseries, and are closed for 75 years from the date of creation of the latest material, currently 2074. There may be personnel records scattered in other series; these fall under privacy and confidentiality laws and patrons are responsible for abiding by these laws.
Also, a small portion of the collection is temporarily closed pending conservation treatment.
Original recordings are closed to use. Some use copies exist; otherwise, listening or viewing copies may need to be created for access.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact staff in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University, or in the University Archives, Records and History Center, North Carolina Central University, before coming to use this collection.
Provenance
The North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives were received by the Duke University David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library and by the North Carolina Central University University Archives, Records and History Center as a gift in 2009, and 2016.
Collection Arrangement
The North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company archives are arranged in the following series, described more fully in this collection guide: Company Offices (86 boxes), Corporate History Files (2 boxes), Digital Media (3 boxes), Exhibit Materials (25 boxes), Memorabilia and Artifacts (16 boxes), Other Organizations (9 boxes), Photographic Materials (24 boxes), Printed Materials (51 boxes), Recordings (5 boxes and 19 film cans), Social Groups and Events (1 box), and Scrapbooks (6 boxes). There are Oversize Materials sections consisting of 54 flat boxes and 10 oversize folders) listed most often after each relevant series in this collection guide.
The Company Offices Series comprises records from selected offices: Actuary, Agency, Auditing, Controller, Corporate Planning, Executive Committee, Facilities, Medical Department, Office of the President (the largest subseries; some restrictions), Public Relations, and Personnel Files (restricted). These subseries are described further in this collection guide.
Historical Chronology
North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Presidents
1898-1919 John Merrick
1919-1923 Dr. Aaron McDuffie Moore
1923-1952 Charles C. Spaulding, Sr.
1952-1958 William J. Kennedy, Jr.
1959-1967 Asa T. Spaulding, Sr.
1968-1972 Joseph W. Goodloe
1972-1990 William J. Kennedy, III
1990-2003 Bert Collins
2004- 2015 James H. Speed
2016- Michael L. Lawrence
Historical Note
Timeline for North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company
1883 The Royal Knights of King David, a fraternal organization, formed by John Merrick, John Wright, W. A. Day, J. D. Morgan, and T. J. Jones to provide insurance for African Americans, chiefly for burials
1898 Inspired by the Royal Knights of King David, North Carolina Mutual and Provident Association founded by John Merrick, Dr. Aaron Moore, P. W. Dawkins, D. T. Watson, W. G. Pearson, E. A. Johnson and J. E. Shepard John Merrick, born during slavery, named first president; Dr. Aaron Moore, first medical director
1899 North Carolina Mutual incorporated by the North Carolina General Assembly, began doing business selling burial insurance
1900 Charles Clinton (C.C.) Spaulding named general manager
1901 Dr. Aaron Moore and John Merrick founded the Lincoln Hospital in Durham to serve African Americans, with Moore as its first superintendent
1903 First full-time insurance agents hired NCM began to buy lots in Durham and build houses for influx of black workers Launch of first internal publication: The North Carolina Mutual
1907 NCM founded and provided capital for Mechanics and Farmers Bank in Durham, to better serve African Americans NCM began issuing ordinary whole life policies in $100, $200, and $500 face amounts
1910 Merrick-Moore-Spaulding Land Company formed; as NCM real estate subsidiary, constructed hundreds of low-cost rental houses in African American neighborhoods in Durham
1919 Death of President John Merrick; Dr. A. M. Moore appointed as successor NCM charter amended, changing the name to North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company
1920-1921 Dr. Donnell, new director of Medical Department, organized modern medical facilities in new Home Office
1923 C.C. Spaulding became president after the death of Dr. Moore
1943 The Liberty Ship S.S. John Merrick built, named in honor of the company's first president, was launched from Wilmington, N.C.; participated in the invasion of France in June 1944, making many voyages ferrying troops, tanks and supplies between English ports and Utah Beach; returned to Brooklyn, New York, April 1945
1948 North Carolina Mutual marked its golden anniversary, producing short film, Success Story
1950 The company reached its goal of having $200 million of life insurance in force
1952 William J. Kennedy, Jr. appointed president after the death of C. C. Spaulding
1959 Asa T. Spaulding appointed president after William J. Kennedy, Jr.'s retirement from the office
1960 Director of Medical Department, Dr. Donnell, retired, succeeded by Dr. Charles Watts
1966 The company dedicated its headquarters on Chapel Hill Street with Vice President Hubert H. Humphrey as the keynote speaker
1967 The Board of Directors established the Merrick-Moore-Spaulding National Achievement Award
1968 Joseph W. Goodloe became president after Asa T. Spaulding's retirement from the office
1971 NCM broke into "Billion Dollar League" by having more than one billion dollars of insurance in force
1972 William J. Kennedy, III became president after Joseph Goodloe's retirement from the office
1983 Opening of the Heritage Room, a pictorial exhibit of the company's history
1986 The company forms NCM Capital Management Group, Inc. to expand its presence in the financial arena and to diversify its business and investment mix
1987 Director of Medical Department, Dr. Charles Watts, retired, succeeded by Dr. John Daniel, Jr.; several years later, Medical Department is discontinued
1990 Bert Collins appointed president and CEO after William Kennedy III's retirement from the office
1995 Board member Thelma J. Smith was named chair of the audit committee; first woman to head a major NCM committee
1997 NCM licensed to operate in 22 states and the District of Columbia with offices in 11 states and Washington, D.C., and more than $9 billion of insurance in force
1998 NCM celebrated its centennial anniversary
2004 James H. Speed, Jr. appointed president and CEO after Bert Collins' retirement from the office
Founded in 1898 and headquartered in Durham, North Carolina, the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company is the oldest currently active African American-owned insurance company in the world. Its name changed in 2016 to NC Mutual to reflect its diversity of services beyond life insurance.
Related Material
Asa and Elna Spaulding Papers,
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
C.C. Spaulding Papers,
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Lincoln Hospital Records,
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
North Carolina Mutual Digital Collection,
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Charles DeWitt Watts Papers,
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
William A. Clement Papers,
Wilson Special Collections Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
Collection Overview
The records in the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives document the history of the oldest currently active African American insurance company in the United States. The materials date from 1850 to 2008, with the majority of the items dating from 1898 to 2008, and cover nearly all aspects concerning the operation, management, and milestones of NC Mutual (NCM). The archive comprises corporate office files, including the offices of five company presidents; annual statements, reports, surveys, and memos; legal and financial files; original life insurance policies and other documents; advertising, internal and external publications, pamphlets, posters, and other print material; training material; many historic photographs; public relations and outreach material; memorabilia; and audiovisual recordings. The bulk of the collection concerns the company's home office in Durham, N.C. but there is a significant amount of material that relates to NCM district offices located throughout the United States, particularly in the South, as well as records that refer to other related organizations such as insurance companies and financial institutions.
The collection contributes significantly to documentation on the history of African American businesses in the United States, particularly in the South, and on the socioeconomic status of African Americans in the South in the 20th century. There is also valuable information on public health issues affecting 20th-century African Americans and public health programming created by NC Mutual as well as other agencies. In addition, through company records and many ephemeral publications such as obituaries, the collection offers detailed documentation of the work status and personal lives of the company's many employees and their life insurance customers, predominantly African American women and men.
The collection is rich in print materials, and includes nearly complete runs of three company publications: The Mutual (1903-1929), The Whetstone (1924-1998), and The Weekly Review (1925-1998). It is also notable for public relations materials dating from the earliest years to the mid-2000s, including advertising ephemera, materials related to advertising campaigns, and other items. Additionally, there are records of NCM's extensive community outreach such as public health, mentoring, and scholarship programs, and documents relating to the company's ties with Durham's churches such as White Rock Baptist, and with other organizations such as Mechanics and Farmers Bank.
Corporate office files form the bulk of the collection, covering nearly every aspect of the company's operations and activities from its founding in 1898. There are extensive correspondence files as well as meeting notes and minutes, many legal and financial reports, and surveys of the insurance industry. Materials relating to a published history of NCM written by one of its presidents, William Kennedy Jr., are located in the Office of the Presidents Series. Company presidents represented most substantially in the files include: William Kennedy Jr. (1952-1958), Asa T. Spaulding (1959-1967), Joseph Goodloe (1968-1972), William Kennedy III (1972-1990), and Bert Collins (1990-2003). Earlier and later presidents and leaders, including founders Merrick and Moore, and presidents C.C. Spaulding and James Speed are also represented in smaller amounts of material. Personnel records are also present and are closed to use until 2074, 75 years after the date of most recent record.
Among the several thousand photographs in the collection, hundreds date from the first decades following the company's founding, and offer important and vivid historical evidence concerning NCM's history, its employees and their families, and the history of Durham, N.C. Many are oversize, and feature twenty panoramic photographs of conventions and other events from the early to mid-20th century. The collection also contains photographs of founders Merrick and Moore and their families, NC Mutual office buildings throughout its history, and many large photographic portraits of senior administration from the earliest years to the mid-2000s. Other photos capture employees at banquets and conventions throughout the company's history; some large sets of images from the early to mid-20th century document employee's homes as well. From the historic photographs and other images not represented in the collection, NCM created a permanent exhibit in its home office's "Heritage Hall" commemorating the company's history; these exhibit images, panels, and labels are also preserved in this collection.
Acquired and jointly curated by the North Carolina Central University's University Archives, Records, and History Center, and the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture at Duke University.
Advertising -- Insurance; African American business enterprises -- History; African American business enterprises -- North Carolina -- History; African American women -- Employment -- History; African Americans -- Economic conditions -- North Carolina -- Durham -- 20th century; African Americans -- Health and hygiene; African Americans in advertising; African Americans -- Medical care -- 20th century; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- History; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Photographs; Insurance companies, American -- History; Insurance companies -- Employees; Insurance companies -- Management; Industries -- North Carolina -- Durham; African Americans -- Diseases; African Americans -- Employment -- History; Insurance; Insurance companies -- North Carolina -- Periodicals; Life insurance -- History; Durham (N.C.) -- Church history; Durham (N.C.) -- Economic conditions; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Durham (N.C.) -- Pictorial works; Durham (N.C.) -- Social conditions; North Carolina -- Economic conditions; Southern States -- Economic conditions; Calendars; CD-ROMs; DVDs; Electronic records; Ephemera; Film; Negatives (photographs); Photographs; Sound recordings; Videotapes; Slides (photographs); Watts, Charles DeWitt; North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Speed, James; University Archives, Records, and History Center (North Carolina Central University); Spaulding, Asa T. (Asa Timothy), 1902-1990; Spaulding, C. C. (Charles Clinton), 1874-1952; Collins, Bert; Merrick, John, 1859-1919; Moore, A. M. (Aaron McDuffie), 1863-1923; Kennedy, William Jesse, 1889-1985; Kennedy, William, III; Goodloe, Joseph W.
- Company Offices, 1850, 1898-2008 and undated; 1920-2000; 86 boxes plus oversize containers
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged in the following subseries named after North Carolina Mutual departments and offices: Actuary, Agency in Force, Auditing, Controller, Corporate Planning, Executive Committee, Facilities, Medical Department, Office of the President, Public Relations, and Personnel Files (closed). There is also an oversize section at the end of each subseries or smaller subgrouping. The Office of the President Series holds the records from the following presidents: William J. Kennedy, Jr., Asa T. Spaulding, Sr., Joseph W. Goodloe, William J. Kennedy, III, and Bert Collins. Company office functions and spaces are also represented in other formats in the Exhibits, Photographic Material, Memorabilia and Artifacts, and Recordings Series.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  The material in the Office of the President is restricted for 25 years from the date of the end of the presidency in question, unless written permission is granted by North Carolina Mutual. The Personnel Files subgrouping is closed to public access for 75 years from date of creation of the most recent record, or 2074.]
  - Actuary Office, 1952, 1969, 1974-2001 and undated; 1980-1987
    The records relate to the Actuary Office's responsibilities of risk assessment in life insurance, investments, pensions, and other company activities and policies. Organized into two categories: Reports for the Board of Directors and Executive Committee, and Actuary Files. Actuary files include memos and consultants' studies and plans. The bulk of the material was created in the 1980s.
    - Reports for the Board of Directors and Executive Committee
      - Report of the Actuary to the Board of Directors, 1980-1998, 10 folders (Box 1)
      - Report of the Actuary to the Board of Directors, 1999-2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Board of Directors meeting minutes with memos from Actuary, 1980-1983 (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee meeting minutes with memos from Actuary, 1980-1983 (Box 2)
    - Actuary Files
      - Federal Home Loan Bank of Atlanta, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
      - Hay Consultants: compensation study, 1985 (Box 2)
      - Hay Consultants: incentive plan, 1985 (Box 2)
      - Industrial insurance system conversion, 1983 and undated (Box 2)
      - Jamison, Eaton, and Wood policy statements, 1985 (Box 2)
      - Long Range Forecasting and Surplus Study, 1969 (Box 2)
      - Memoranda and notes, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Mortgage loan computer systems, 1986 (Box 2)
      - NCNB investment management, 1985 (Box 2)
      - Planning New Horizons, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Report of the Controller, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Rolling Hills Associates, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Stellar Communications, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
      - Annual statement files, 1974-1987, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Bulletins and memos, 1952 (Box 3)
      - Commercial series, 1977-1983 and undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Legal agreements, 1980-1983 and undated (Box 3)
      - National Cable Television Association convention, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Position papers, 1986 (Box 3)
      - WMGB/WQKS, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Financial Statements (oversize)
      - Commercial series financial statement, 1982, box size: 22x30 inches (Box OV1)
      - Statements and memos, 1984-1987, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV2)
  - Agency in Force Office, 1850, 1920-1994 and undated
    The center of company operations, the Agency in Force Office handles all company sales of policies, and is staffed by agents in the field, their supervisors, district managers, and home office representatives. By 1948, the company already had over 1,000 agents in force throughout the South. The material of this subseries includes Executive Committee directives and decisions, agency-related files and ledger books, and the G.W. Cox papers. The Agency files contain salary information, several issues of The Weekly Review, memos, and manuals. The subseries also contains policy loan certificates and claims dismissal correspondence with the Receiver from Woodmen Union Life Insurance Company.
    Some materials in boxes 3, 4, and 4-A through 4-D are fragile and in need of preservation. Please contact Research Services to use this material, as contents must be photocopied before being handled.
    - Certificate of membership policy, Amey Husband, 1902 Oct. [photostat copy - reduced size] (Box 3)
    - Claims bulletins and memos, 1939, 1945, 1952, 1957-1959, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Policy loan certificates, 1923-1937, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence regarding Woodmen Union Life Insurance Company and policies, 1921-1937, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence regarding Woodmen Union Life Insurance Company and policies, 1931-1937, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - G.W. Cox papers, 1936-1957, 7 folders (Box 4)
      [Materials in this box are fragile and in need of preservation. Please contact Research Services to use this material, as contents should be photocopied before being handled.]
    - Policies, circa 1930s (Box 4-A)
      [Materials in this box are fragile and in need of preservation. Please contact Research Services to use this material, as contents should be further processed before being handled.]
    - Policies, circa 1930s (Box 4-B)
    - Policies, circa 1930s (Box 4-C)
    - Field Bulletin Book No. 1, 1922-1957 (Box 4-D)
      Memos to agents in field, #1-252, were filed in binder with Asa T. Spaulding's initials. Appears to be complete run. To better preserve contents, the memos were disbound and foldered. Arranged in reverse chronological order.
    - Executive Committee directives and decisions, 1956-1984, 14 folders (Box 5)
    - Executive Committee memos, 1985-1988 (Box 5)
    - NCM Agent's manual, circa 1965 (Box 6)
    - John T. Carey papers: photos for Spartanburg, SC district, 1960-1971 and undated (Box 6)
    - John T. Carey papers: memorabilia, 1901, 1917, 1948, 1957-1958, 1965, 1974-1984, and undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - John T. Carey papers: retiree correspondence and information from L. B. Frasier, 1984-1986 (Box 6)
    - John T. Carey papers: miscellaneous memos and documents, 1947, 1963, 1976-1978, and undated (Box 6)
    - John T. Carey papers: certificates for community service, 1981-1983 (Box 6)
    - Annual statements, 1921-1927, 1947, 1958 (Box 7)
    - Job duty charts, undated (Box 7)
    - Managerial training, undated (Box 7)
    - NCM Digest of Union Contracts, 1966-1969 (Box 7)
    - NCM forum, 1956 (Box 7)
    - New home office, 1962-1966 (Box 7)
    - NIA Institute in Agency Management conference, 1959 (Box 7)
    - Salary scales and wage memos, 1920-1954, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Weekly Review, 1929-1937, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Manual of Instructions, 1975-1977 and undated, 2 folders (Box 7)